this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet.
as a radio brings you relevant and detailed discussions and interviews on software engineering topics every two weeks.
thanks to our audience and the partners listed on our website for supporting the program.
hello, welcome listeners to this somewhat different as a radio episode.
we've called it more or less state of the union.
and we want to talk a little bit about the current state of SU radio with me on this episode.
there should be on the other end of Skype Michael.
hello, hello, hello, and matthean should also be around.
yeah, I'm here. hi, hello, hello.
yeah, well I guess we wanted to let our listeners know what the state of affairs is in SU radio.
people might have noticed that we reduced the, you know, the release frequency from every 10 days to every two weeks not too long ago.
and basically we're kind of struggling to produce the content.
that's basically the story, and we wanted to let you know what our plans are.
I guess one thing we should do right now is to give you a little bit of an overview.
of how the current team structure and se radio looks like.
yeah, so it's basically for interviewers.
this is Marcus of course,
not in, then Robert who joined us lately from the US, and it's me.
and then we have a bunch of basically support stuff.
yeah, so we have we have of course Christie, who does all the audio processing and actually creates the mp3 files and uploads them.
and you know as the introduction, all of that.
we have a phone call who handles the publishing and you know uploads the mp3s.
makes sure that everybody rides the show notes in these things.
we of course have bumped who works on the website itself and keeps it going.
and we have attila who deals with a spam.
he's the person who looks at all the comments and removes them if they're crap.
and i guess it's it's fair to say that if we didn't have the back office, as i'd like to call them, we'd be in really bad shape.
I mean we really appreciate the help of these people often nobody sees or hears them.
yeah, so Lee thanks focal, thanks Christy, thanks pendant, thanks attila.
yeah, thanks for me too.
i guess we probably have what i've stopped in the mean time if they didn't do that work.
yeah, definitely, which brings us back to the to the core issue.
which is that we're kind of noticing that you know the three of us at least we're basically running out of time and out of ideas. i guess that's that's the problem.
yeah, i mean looking back you have noticed that markers that most of the episodes...
i can speak only for me right now.
having a job with 40 50 hours per week and family, i mean there's only so much time left to do recordings.
and because of that I have limited well resources, limited time for for recording.
and I guess we we all fall back kind of to the limit or three to four episodes per person, right?
yeah, it's basically the same issue for me.
I do all this this stuff in my free time, my spare time.
and it's it's fun and it's great, and I think I I still have a lot of ideas for for new episodes.
but my time is just so limited that I can I can't do so much episode that I that I would like to do.
so nobody nobody's just paying me for that, so it's that's maybe that's an issue. yeah, we talked about this recently.
you you told me how long you actually work on these episodes on average, and I was a little bit surprised.
you mentioned something about eight hours.
yeah, I think per episode I I think I invest eight to ten or twelve hours for that.
including the preparation, talking with with the interviewee about the content.
doing the actual recording, which which needs maybe one and a half hour or so.
and then doing the the post-processing and editing the content of the episode, not the sound.
the sound is done by I think but Christy, and he does a great job.
but the content I need to I need to edit, and and that's that takes me a lot of time.
I'm not a sound editor professional, so maybe that's one of the one of the reasons.
so and that basically means that if you do five episodes a year, that's basically a week.
it's basically week and it's basically a week of week of spare time for me.
right, so yeah I have to spend my holidays more or less on that.
yeah, so one thing I did for example in some of the more recent episodes was that I that I cut back significantly on on editing.
for example the episode on on C++ or X with with Scott, or the episode with olivine II, or the one with with Gilad bracha on you speak.
I basically didn't edit anything.
they were talking really nice and there was not a lot to do.
and you know when it went when we started as you radio, I basically edit it out every every M and every nd every stumbling.
I don't do this anymore, and this is one of the consequences just to speed up the editing process.
yeah, maybe I do maybe on the opposite I - I do too less episodes - to get better in the editing.
because if I would do every day this kind of editing it would would speed up I think now.
but then on the other side we might need to say that would be a full-time job for me here, so I don't know.
yeah, one thing we try to do in the past was to motivate additional people to be part of the team.
and and Robert Robert blumen who he introduced only recently, he is he's a good example of how this actually can work.
he does a lot of work, he is very enthusiastic.
and he has already produced a number of more a number of additional episodes which will be published soon.
but we've also had a couple of people who wanted to join, who produced maybe one episode or two.
and then notice that it's too much work, and then it fizzled out and they kind of left again or things like that.
and that was actually quite frustrating.
because it took us you know some effort to get these people on board and you know introduce them to the overall process.
and help them editing and things like that.
so growing the team isn't something that's easily done, I guess that's what I'm trying to get it.
yeah, but I would also say that I think it's it's great that those people and said that they would like to join in.
it's a it's great the day they they tried it, and they yeah it's it's too much time as I can perfectly understand that.
so no that's not the point but I agree.
and I you know that's I'm not saying they they shouldn't have tried or anything.
but just saying it's not as easy as we maybe thought to get additional people on the team.
and and solve the problem by having different people and more people.
yeah, and this is not to say that we won't try it in the future.
I guess we will try it in the future, but on both sides we should be careful, right?
yeah, which on the other hand means that you know if you're listening to this now, if you're hearing this now.
and I mean you really if you really if you want to join.
we would really love to have new team members, interviewing team members, editors as we probably call them.
but if you want to join please make sure you actually have the time in your serious.
so yeah, maybe one thing Marcus,
why did you cut back from those many many episodes down to what we are now up to announcing?
for me personally there are several reasons.
one is that many of the topics that I'm interested in, and where I can easily get at the people, you know find people to talk to, I've done these.
so it's for me I don't I don't have as many ideas as I have had in the beginning.
the other thing is that I I also do other podcasts now, specifically this Omega how stuff.
which which is you know everything except software, and personally it's just more fun for me now.
because this is you know more interesting, it's newer.
I guess for all for all for all of us it's true that when we started as your radio four and a half or four years ago.
it was new, it was exciting, and and we had a lot of ideas.
and now it has become kind of routine, and and so we don't have that.
at least I don't have that that enthusiasm anymore.
so there needs to be another motivation, another driver.
and that hasn't actually really you know appeared it did there is no other driver at this point.
and so that's why I don't do as many episodes anymore as I used to.
for me it's the case that well I never had that much time, so I basically stayed at my same level of producing episodes.
and I continuously find new interesting topics that we we would like to talk about.
but also that we think is interesting to to listen to.
it's just that the topics that I'm most familiar with, they are actually I guess produced.
and so I'm going to focus on new topics where I learn in the future.
and where I find an interesting interview are interviewing mm-hmm I could good then in the view on the interesting topic.
yeah, I mean the thing is maybe su radio will also change focus a little bit over time.
you've already introduced Michael, you've already introduced some more management oriented topics.
which we probably wouldn't have done four years ago.
and I think that that reflects our personal change in evolution as well.
I think for me is it's mostly the time the time issue.
so I think I still have a lot of ideas and a lot of motivation to do new episodes.
but the times just just it's just too limited to do all this stuff in my time, right?
it's interesting for me that the time to do the episode is probably a little bit less because I have more practice editing.
but for me the problem is you know not the time it takes, but to find the time.
I'm travelling quite a lot, and I can only recall this stuff when I'm at home.
and so finding an actual spot where I can do the recording, where I am home and where the guest is at home, that's that's more and more challenging.
another thing we we thought about recently, or not seriously, but we try to play it through.
what's the idea of making se radio paid content?
so you'd have to I don't know pay I don't know 20 20 euros a year to get the SU radio content.
and we currently have about twenty thousand listeners.
and assuming that only 10% of those twenty thousand would be willing to pay, we'd be at about 40,000 euros a year.
which if we consider faulty episodes would make it a thousand euros per episode, which for a day of work is okay, right?
Martin, we actually discussed this, right?
so we thought about that, but basically we noticed it's probably not gonna work.
first of all problem is that if we did that and really and only 10% of our listeners would kind of join the paid content thing.
then we would only have let's say one to two thousand listeners.
which makes su radio much less attractive for potential guests.
and also we would probably have to pay the guests.
because if they come on the show and we earn money with it, why shouldn't they get any money?
so we'd have all these financial issues.
and then of course currently you can just download the episodes and give it to other people.
there is no there is no black market.
as soon as we'd make this paid content we'd have to probably put DRM on them.
and so it's basically it doesn't work.
so even if we wanted we probably couldn't make this work.
we also thought about you know sponsoring.
we recently got an offer from an American podcast advertising company.
they offered us - you know if you listen to this week in tech and the other Leo Laporte podcasts, you know the usual suspects.
we were approached by audible, and we actually did one episode at one time I think.
but the point is basically for three episodes a month we would get in total 80 euros or even 80 dollars.
so it's it's not worth the hassle.
because if we want wanted to do it by you know with advertising, we'd have to have 10 or 20 times more listeners which we don't have. so that doesn't work either.
so in other words money is not something that could work.
we do of course appreciate a lot that the donations we get from time to time.
a couple of you have subscribed or sent donations from time to time.
we've bought audio equipment with that, and we've you know paid for the website design and other things like that, and we really appreciate it.
but the point is it's not enough to make AC radio something we would do for the money, right right.
so um so that's a long story.
anything you guys want to add to that before we get to the point?
no nothing to read right now please.
yeah, I think we discussed all the or we talk talked about all the issues.
so who wants to announce the point?
the point is we switch to four weekly releases of our episodes, yeah basically once per month.
and personally I am I'm not necessarily very happy about that.
because podcasts that only come up come out once a month, I don't know how how many people will actually stick around.
we also thought about stopping sa radio, you know not continuing until it dies.
but rather stopping it while it's good, and and you know making sure that everybody keeps it you know as a positive.
you know back then when we still had as a radio and it was good blah blah.
but we decided to try the the monthly release.
this basically means three to four episodes for each of us, for Robert Martin Marcus and me.
if we have additional content, I guess we will opt for releasing in-between.
if that is the case and we feel the the material needs to get out.
but for now we envision basically the monthly release.
which leaves us enough time to produce high quality episodes.
and on the other hand have a well undisturbed business life and quiet family life.
I mean I guess the point is as a radio is a community thing, right?
I mean there is a couple of people who do this as a labor of love as it's called.
and if you want to get more content, I mean join us help us produce more, right? so I guess that's that's it.
is there anything else much else Martin here you want to you want to add today?
I hope our listeners don't mind too much our change and stay with us.
we at least our committed as before producing high-quality episodes that are fun to listen.
yes, I'm saying to me, and I hope all the people stay with us and keep listening to our 1-month episodes.
and I'm looking forward to producing a lot of great episodes in the future.
and hope that this thing will go on.
okay, so thanks me here, thanks Martin.
and once again if you want more content join us help us. fine, bye, XY.
thanks for listening to software engineering radio.
software engineer radio is an educational program brought to you by hillside Europe.
if you want more information about the podcast and all the other episodes visit our website at SE - radio dotnet.
if you want to support us you can donate to the SU radio team by our website.
or you can advertise for se radio, for example by clicking on the Digg reddit delicious links and the slash dot button.
to contact the team please send email to team at SC - radio net.
or if you're specific to an episode please use the comments facility on the website so other people can react to your comments.
this episode of se radio as well as all other episodes are licensed under the creative commons 2.5 license.
please see the website for details.
thanks to Charlie Crow and the pot site music network for the music used in this show.
the song is called Vegas Achtung.